<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Devops on The Linuxian</title>
    <link>http://www.linuxian.com/categories/devops/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Devops on The Linuxian</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Nov 2017 21:47:06 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://www.linuxian.com/categories/devops/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Join Linux into Domain</title>
      <link>http://www.linuxian.com/2017/11/join-linux-into-domain/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Nov 2017 21:47:06 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.linuxian.com/2017/11/join-linux-into-domain/</guid>
      <description>If you are looking for how to add Linux ( CentOS ) into Microsoft domain controller ( Active Directory directory), then this articial useful for you.
Introduction I was working on Highly secure big data infra, where all services access where configure by Ranger ACL&amp;rsquo;s. the services were interact with Kafka, Hadoop, Hive etc. it&amp;rsquo;s uses Keytab files for authentications and the basic requirement were client should be part of the domain controller.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interact Kafka using python Kafka client</title>
      <link>http://www.linuxian.com/2017/11/interact-kafka-using-python-kafka-client/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Nov 2017 02:42:14 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.linuxian.com/2017/11/interact-kafka-using-python-kafka-client/</guid>
      <description>In this tutorial you will learn how to interact Kafka using python module. this will help to you write your own ansible module to handle Kafka or monitoring script to check Kafka.
There are two main libraries for kafka in python, pykafka and kafka-python, we will see pykafka.
Install pykafka pip install pykafka Kafka configuration With all settings to run Kafka server, you need to make sure following entry should be enabled on your Kafka server.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Authorization service and frontend for Docker registry</title>
      <link>http://www.linuxian.com/2017/11/authorization-service-and-frontend-for-docker-registry/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Nov 2017 01:01:10 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.linuxian.com/2017/11/authorization-service-and-frontend-for-docker-registry/</guid>
      <description>I have been working on improvement of existing CI/CD pipeline. were having some challenges like disk space, manage images and accessing data with docker registry server. I plan to use something else which could solve this issue, I came across the nice tool Portus docker registry. It has lots of features like Search for images, Image Favorites, LDAP authentication, Comment function to images etc.
Portus architecture and Component  Portus : Portus is a WebUI, Rails application that performs authentication and authorization.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>