<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The Linuxian</title>
    <link>http://www.linuxian.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on The Linuxian</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 May 2017 23:26:07 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://www.linuxian.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Setup Private Docker Registry</title>
      <link>http://www.linuxian.com/posts/setup-private-docker-registry/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 May 2017 23:26:07 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.linuxian.com/posts/setup-private-docker-registry/</guid>
      <description>Introduction In this tutorial we are going to learn about Docker registry and how to setup your own private registry with self-sign certificates.
I hope you have read previous posts on docker basics and it&amp;rsquo;s concepts.
What is Docker Registry? A registry is a storage and content delivery system, holding named Docker images, available in different tagged versions.
There are to types of Registry:
 Public Registry : The default registry for all images.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AWS volume script</title>
      <link>http://www.linuxian.com/posts/aws-volume-script/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.linuxian.com/posts/aws-volume-script/</guid>
      <description>Here is small useful script which will help you to attach volume on ec2 instances without login into the AWS console.
I&amp;rsquo;m connected to AWS using VPN, so following script will work with private ip but if you are not connected to vpn, then you can change PrivateIpAddress to PublicIp
#!/bin/bash  set -e # Create and Attach Volume to Instace using IP Address  export AWS_ACCESS_KEY_ID=XXX export AWS_SECRET_ACCESS_KEY=XXXXXX export REGION=us-east-1 export AWS_DEFAULT_REGION=$REGION if [[ $# -ne 2 ]] then echo &amp;#34;Usage: $0&amp;lt;hostname|IP&amp;gt; &amp;lt;size&amp;gt;&amp;#34; exit 1 fi msg(){ echo &amp;#34;=========={$@}==========&amp;#34; } get_instance_data(){ # returns ZONE STATUS IP INSTANCE_ID DEVICE  local host=$1 if !</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hands on docker commands</title>
      <link>http://www.linuxian.com/posts/hands-on-docker-commands/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Feb 2017 17:06:58 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.linuxian.com/posts/hands-on-docker-commands/</guid>
      <description>Introduction In the previous tutorial, we have learn about docker and containers and Installation of docker. now we will see how to play with container because handling containers is the sole purpose of all these infrastructure.
1. RUN command docker run hello-world Whats just happend?
Basically once you run above command, it&amp;rsquo;s do following things:
 Check &amp;ldquo;hello-world&amp;rdquo; image is exists or not locally, that&amp;rsquo;s why you see first msg &amp;ldquo;Unable to find.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting started with Docker Basics</title>
      <link>http://www.linuxian.com/posts/getting-started-with-docker/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.linuxian.com/posts/getting-started-with-docker/</guid>
      <description>Introduction In this tutorial we will learn following things:
 What is Containers Why Containers Containers vs VM&amp;rsquo;s What is Docker Docker component and architecture Docker Installation &amp;amp; Setup on CentOS 7 Docker basic commands  In Traditional way of virtualization As we used lot of VMs for dev testing or any R &amp;amp; D purpose or may be for different different VMs for applications, But actually we create VM then we install OS then we host our application in that OS, so its actually takes much resouces.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ansible_basics</title>
      <link>http://www.linuxian.com/posts/ansible_basics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2015 20:14:43 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.linuxian.com/posts/ansible_basics/</guid>
      <description>This Guid will help you to learn Ansible basics and some practical stuff.
What is Ansible ? Ansible is a radically simple IT automation platform that makes your applications and systems easier to deploy. Avoid writing scripts or custom code to deploy and update your applications— automate in a language that approaches plain English, using SSH, with no agents to install on remote systems
In Summery:  Simple IT Automation tool It&amp;rsquo;s Configuration Management tool Provision tool &amp;ndash;&amp;gt; Create New VM/(AWS)Instance Package Installations Deployment  Why Ansible ?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Useful Linux Commands</title>
      <link>http://www.linuxian.com/posts/hands-on-linux-commands/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.linuxian.com/posts/hands-on-linux-commands/</guid>
      <description>In this post, I want to list some useful shell scripts/commands, keyboard shortcuts , some may be already known to you and some may not be, but nonetheless I feel its my duty to share some not so trivial things to search and find that easily sometimes, also I needed a quick reference of these which may be useful for Linux System Admin, coders including me in future, so here we go.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Send password expiry notification to nix users using Python script</title>
      <link>http://www.linuxian.com/posts/python-script-display-and-mail-users-account-expiry-details/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.linuxian.com/posts/python-script-display-and-mail-users-account-expiry-details/</guid>
      <description>Are you Managing N Number of Users and want to check Account Expires and send notification to administrator through Gmail ?
Here is a Python script which will send notification to administrator, which accounts are going to expire in 7 days. You are free to use and modify this script for your work.
#!/usr/bin/env python #--------------------------------------------------------- # Name :- checkUsrAccount_Expiry.py v 0.1 Copyleft (c) :) # Pupose :- To check the user account expire status in Linux, unix, BSD etc # Author :- Rahul Patil&amp;lt;http://www.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SED 10 useful commands</title>
      <link>http://www.linuxian.com/posts/sed-10-useful-commands/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.linuxian.com/posts/sed-10-useful-commands/</guid>
      <description>When you are write a script and if you want to edit some file from command line, then you can use sed. 10 Basic examples that I’ve provided here, you’ll find using command line more enjoyable and fun.
About SED
sed is an Non-interactive stream editor.
Features  scripting languages work primarily with text file. programmable editor. accept command-line option and can be scripted ( sed -f script_name ) GNU versions supports POSIX (Grep) and (Egrep) regexes Does not operate on the source file , by default , its only print the changes in source file exept ( -i option).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>about_me</title>
      <link>http://www.linuxian.com/aboute-me/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.linuxian.com/aboute-me/</guid>
      <description>
Just a Simple guy with Linux experience..
I simply like scripting,coding and helping others is a fulfilling way to stay up to date and give something back to the community and the web from which I learned so much.
Currently Working as Big Data DevOps Engineer.
echo &amp;#34;You reach me at :&amp;#34;; tr a-z@. n-za-m.@ &amp;lt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt; ybtvaenuhy90.tznvy@pbz   Linkedin GitHub GooglePlus Nixcraft  </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>